Guide to the Montana Typographical Conference Records 1937-1984
Montana Historical Society Archives
Montana Typographical Conference Records
1937-1984
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 321
Montana Typographical Conference
2 linear feet of shelf space
The Montana Typographical Conference was the state-wide organization for the International Typographical Union. There were local unions in many cities around the state. Records include interoffice correspondence (1958-1980), correspondence with the local unions (1953-1984), correspondence with the international union (1959-1984), and general correspondence (1955-1984) with the Montana State AFL-CIO and others. In addition there are financial records, local union contracts, convention minutes (1953-1984), organizational records, reports, subject files, and miscellany. There is a small subgroup for records of the International Typographical Union.
The National Typographical Union was established in 1852 as the major union in the printing trade. In 1874 it became the International Typographical Union with several Canadian locals. The first Montana local union was formed in Helena in 1867. Gradually additional local unions were established in cities across the state. Initially, the Helena local functioned as the de facto state organization. The Montana Typographical Conference was formed in 1929 to coordinate the work of the local unions. The objectives of the conference included organizing the printing trade around the state, promoting the training of printers, urging buyers of printed material to patronize union shops, encouraging cooperation among locals, and assisting them in contract negotiations. During the Depression and war years the conference was largely inactive. After World War II, the conference became a leading factor in the printers' union statewide. It became actively involved in apprenticeship programs, in training in new printing technologies, in relations with the Montana State AFL-CIO, and contract discussions. Although membership in the local unions was declining rapidly due to new technology, the conference remained vigorous into the early 1980s. The Montana Typographical Conference folded about 1984. After briefly considering a merger with the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, the International Typographical Union was absorbed into the Communications Workers of America in 1987.
Content Description:
Records include interoffice correspondence (1958-1980) among the officers and board members of the Conference; correspondence with the local unions (1953-1984), correspondence with the international union (1959-1984), and general correspondence (1955-1984) with the Montana State AFL-CIO and others. Among the major correspondents are Stanley E. Thurston, Breen J. Hamry, Konrad E. Braaten, Fred W. Richards, Ben T. Melugin, Harry L. Billings, Sam Butler, Edwin R. Wakefield, Bernard Kempa, Frank E. Winkler, and Donald R. Schmit. In addition, there are financial records, consisting of financial reports (1956-1984) of the secretary-treasurer, local union dues payments (1960-1977), and other items. There are scattered contracts of local unions including Billings, Great Falls, Bozeman, and Miles City. There are convention minutes (1953-1984), including resolutions passed and convention programs. Organizational records include constitutions and bylaws for the conference and for the Billings and Butte local unions; delegate reports, and lists of local unions. There are annual reports (1952-1956), reports of the secretary-treasurer (1966-1968), a report of the president (1973?), and reports from local unions. Subject files include legislation, the Montana Farmer-Labor Institute, the Montana Mechanical Clinic, the Montana United Labor Council, and the Rocky Mountain Labor School. In addition there are miscellaneous other materials including a history of the Montana Typographical Conference by Harry L. Billings, writing contest entries, and brochures from a variety of organizations on a variety of issues. There is a small subgroup of records of the International Typographical Union. Included are convention proceedings (1956, 1961); printed material; and a subject file on a proposed merger of ITU with the International Brotherhood of Teamsters in 1984-1985.
Arrangement:
by series
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Newspaper publishing; Printing; Trade-unions--Newspaper employees; Labor unions--Newspaper employees; Montana; Labor History; Publishers and Publishing
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Interoffice Correspondence
  - Montana Typographical Conference (correspondents include Carl A. Steck, George Broeker, Tom Hawkins, Breen J. Hamry, Stanley E. Thurston, Konrad E. Braaten), 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Montana Typographical Conference (correspondents include Tom Hawkins, Breen J. Hamry, Stanley E. Thurston, Konrad E. Braaten, Ben T. Melugin, Fred W. Richards), 1960 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Montana Typographical Conference (correspondents include Ben T. Melugin, Fred W. Richards, Harry L. Billings, Wally Fournier, Sam Butler, Robert G. Thomas, Leonard L. Barclay, Edwin R. Wakefield), 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Montana Typographical Conference (correspondents include Leonard L. Barclay, Edwin R. Wakefield, Stanley E. Thurston, Harry L. Billings, Breen J. Hamry, Robert G. Thomas, Alfred N. Johnson, Bernard J. Kempa), 1963-1964 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Montana Typographical Conference (correspondents include Stanley E. Thurston, Breen J. Hamry, Bernard J. Kempa, Woodrow J. Wilson, Frank E. Winkler, John Polston), 1965-1966 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Montana Typographical Conference (correspondents include Woodrow J. Wilson, Arvid Lundin, Ralph Ammondson, Donald R. Schmit, Peter J. McKeon), 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Montana Typographical Conference (correspondents include Bernard Kempa, Eugene Fischer, Peter J. McKeon, John Eckenweiler, Dan Berg, Floyd A. Severson), 1971-1980 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Montana local typographical unions (includes Anaconda #255, Billings #398, Bozeman #656, Butte #126, Great Falls #256, Havre #764, Helena #95, Kalispell #723, Lewistown #550, Livingston #489, Miles City #631, Missoula #277), 1953-1973 (Box-folder 1 / 9-13)
  - Montana local typographical unions (includes Anaconda #255, Billings #398, Bozeman #656, Butte #126, Great Falls #256, Havre #764, Helena #95, Kalispell #723, Lewistown #550, Livingston #489, Miles City #631, Missoula #277), 1974-1984 (Box-folder 2 / 1-3)
  - International Typographical Union, 1959-1984 (Box-folder 2 / 4-5)
- General Correspondence
  - Montana State AFL-CIO (re organizing, training programs, "right-to-work" legislation, sales tax, legislation, politics, etc.), 1959-1984 (Box-folder 2 / 6-15)
  - Chronological (correspondents include Montana state agencies, printing companies, politicians, etc.), 1955-1984 (Box-folder 3 / 1-5)
- Financial Records
  - Anaconda Company strike fund, 1968 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Audit Committee reports, 1964-1965, n.d. (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Bank records, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - Financial reports of Secretary-Treasurer [some years missing], 1956-1984 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
  - Journal and check register, 1959-1981 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
  - Local union dues payments, 1960-1977 (Box-folder 3 / 11)
  - Miscellaneous (includes bills, receipts, etc.), 1960-1966 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
- Legal Documents
  - Contracts: Billings Typographical Union #398 and Billings Gazette; Great Falls Typographical Union #256 and Great Falls Tribune; Bozeman Typographical Union #656 and Artcraft Printers; Miles City Typographical Union #631 and Star Printing Company; blank sample contract, 1964-1983 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
- Minutes
  - Convention minutes, resolutions, programs, 1953-1984, n.d. (Box-folder 3 / 14-21)
- Organizational Records
  - Constitutions and bylaws, 1937, 1955-1982 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - Constitutions and bylaws: Billings Typographcial Union #398; Butte Typographical Union #126, 1952, 1966 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
  - Delegate credentials, 1959-1969, n.d. (Box-folder 4 / 3)
  - Delegate reports (gives data on local unions), 1961 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
  - Local unions contract data, 1960s (Box-folder 4 / 5)
  - Local union lists, n.d. (Box-folder 4 / 6)
- Reports
  - Annual reports, 1952-1956 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
  - Delegates' reports on Montana Typographical Conference conventions, seminars, etc., 1954-1963 (Box-folder 4 / 8)
  - Reports from local unions (also includes winning entries in contest "My future in printing under ITU training"), 1969 (Box-folder 4 / 9)
  - Report of president, 1973? (Box-folder 4 / 10)
  - Reports of secretary-treasurer, 1966-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 4 / 11)
- Subject Files
  - Legislation, 1959-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 4 / 12)
  - Montana Farmer-Labor Institute, 1961 (Box-folder 4 / 13)
  - Montana Mechanical Clinic (re training for new technologies), 1958 (Box-folder 4 / 14)
  - Montana United Labor Council, 1962 (Box-folder 4 / 15)
  - Rocky Mountain Labor School, 1974 (Box-folder 4 / 16)
- Miscellany
  - Advertisements for new printing equipment, 1961? (Box-folder 4 / 17)
  - Election returns for new Constitution and for legislative candidates, 1972 (Box-folder 4 / 18)
  - History of Montana Typographical Conference by Harry Billings, 1963 (Box-folder 4 / 19)
  - "History of the Union Label" (contest entries), 1964? (Box-folder 4 / 20)
  - Legislators' voting record on key union issues, 1971 (Box-folder 4 / 21)
  - Political campaign materials, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 4 / 22)
  - "Right-to-Work" materials, 1958-1966 (Box-folder 4 / 23)
  - Sales tax materials, 1961? (Box-folder 4 / 24)
  - Union advertisement contest entries, n.d. (Box-folder 4 / 25)
  - Miscellaneous (includes advertisements, brochures, blank stationery, Consumer Affairs Council membership certificate, press release, International Typographical Union progressive party materials), n.d. (Box-folder 4 / 26)
- Transfers to other programs
  - Convention photos transferred to Photo Archives; The Typo Bulletin transferred to Library, 1957; 1959-1970 (Box-folder 4 / 27)
- Minutes
  - Convention proceedings, 1956, 1961 (Box-folder 4 / 28-29)
- Printed Material
  - The Bulletin, 1956, 1961 1971-1972 (Box-folder 4 / 30)
  - Contract File [newsletter], 1961-1962 (Box-folder 4 / 31)
  - "Facts about the International Typographical Union", 1956 (Box-folder 4 / 32)
  - ITU Lessons in Printing: Trade Unionism [vol. 6], 1946 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
  - ITU Review, 1961, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 5 / 2)
  - Minimum Wage Scale pamphlets, 1947-1952 (Box-folder 5 / 3)
  - Official Directory of the International Typographical Union (lists international officers, local union jurisdictions, officers of local unions, conferences, local printing trades councils and state conferences), 1984 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
  - Wage Scales, Hours, and Working Conditions pamphlets, 1953-1957 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
- Subject Files
  - Proposed merger of International Typographical Union with International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 6)